I'm 36 years old.
عمري 36 سنة.
My first experience with the video game business
أول تجاربي مع ألعاب الفيديو
was neighbors who were wealthier than us
كانت عندما قام جيراننا الأكثر ثراءً
bringing home an Atari 2600 and playing it.
بإحضار لعبة (أتاري 2600) واللعب بها.
It was a pretty definitive moment for me.
كانت تلك لحظة مصيرية بالنسبة لي.
I also remember going to school, and on an Apple II,
أتذكر أيضًا عندما كنت أذهب إلى المدرسة، وعلى حاسوب Apple II
playing a game called "Where in the World is Carmen Sandiego?"
كنت ألعب لعبة تسمى "أين كارمن ساندييغو بحق السماء؟"
an awesome game,
لعبة رائعة،
which was the first time I played a game in the school context.
وكانت أول مرة ألعب فيها ضمن نطاق المدرسة.
When you ask people about the video game business and what's significant,
عندما تسأل الناس عن تجارة ألعاب الفيديو وما المهم فيها،
most people think that Atari 2600 is really the nexus,
يعتقد معظمهم بأن أتاري 2600 هي صلة الوصل،
the catalyst of the video game business.
العامل المحفز لتجارة ألعاب الفيديو.
But I actually think that "Where in the World is Carmen Sandiego?"
لكن صراحةً، أعتقد أن لعبة "أين كارمن ساندييغو بحق السماء؟"
is probably the most important video game ever made,
هي على الأرجح أهم لعبة فيديو على مر التاريخ.
principally because it was the first and the last time
بشكل رئيسي لأنها المرة الأولى والأخيرة
that parents, teachers and kids all agreed that a video game was awesome.
التي اتفق فيها الآباء والمدرسون والأطفال على أنها لعبة فيديو رائعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, that was a long time ago.
كان هذا منذ وقت طويل
In fact, it was 1987.
في الواقع، كان عام 1987.
And it may surprise you to know
وربما تتفاجأون لمعرفة
that "Where in the World is Carmen Sandiego?" continues to be
أن لعبة "أين كارمن ساندييغو بحق السماء؟" لا تزال
the last substantial giant hit in the entertainment business,
الضربة العملاقة الأخيرة في مجال الترفيه،
despite the fact that it was 1987, which is such an incredibly long time ago,
رغم أنها ابتكرت في عام 1987، وهذا قبل زمن طويل جدًا،
and I'm only 36, so you can do the math.
وأنا عمري 36 فقط، فبإمكانكم الحساب.
Things are completely different today from what they were.
الحياة الآن مختلفة تمامًا عما كانت عليه سابقًا.
Just as a simple example,
مجرد مثال بسيط،
in 1987, we thought this guy was kind of crazy.
في عام 1987، تصورنا أن ذلك الرجل مجنون،
Then we met this dude,
ثم إلتقينا بهذا الرجل،
who has really changed our perspective on that subject.
والذي غير من نظرتنا حول ذاك الأمر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Things have changed.
لقد تغيرت الأمور.
Anti-Bush political humor goes a long way in Western Europe.
تنتشر الفكاهة السياسية المضادة لبوش كثيراً في أوروبا الغربية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, between 1987 and now,
إذاً، بين العام 1987 والوقت الحالي،
I played a lot of this game called "Civilization,"
لعبت الكثير من تلك اللعبة التي تسمى بـ "الحضارة"
which was designed by a guy named Sid Meier.
والتي صممها رجل يدعى "سيد ماير".
In fact, I spent about 8- to 10,000 hours of my life playing "Civilization,"
في الحقيقة، لقد قضيت ما بين 8 إلى 10 آلاف ساعة من عمري، في لعب "الحضارة"
which is a long time I probably should have spent studying.
وهو وقت طويل جداً، كان ينبغي لي قضاءه في الدراسة.
But nonetheless, I managed to turn this love of video games into a job,
ولكن برغم ذلك، تمكنت من تحويل حبي لألعاب الفيديو إلى عمل،
first working on the Game Developers Conference,
في البداية، العمل على مؤتمر مطوري الألعاب،
helping to start the first successful digital distribution company in games,
والمساعدة في إنشاء أول شركة توزيع ألعاب إلكترونية ناجحة،
called Trymedia,
تدعى "تراي ميديا"،
and then now, writing the Gamification blog.
ثم الآن، كتابة مدونة التلعيب.
I'm author of two books on the subject of gamification,
أنا مؤلف لكتابين عن موضوع التلعيب،
including the recent "Gamification by Design," published by O'Reilly.
إضافة إلى الكتاب الأخير "التلعيب عن طريق التصميم" الذي نشره أوه رايلي
And I chair the Gamification Summit,
كما أرأس قمة التلعيب،
which is an event that brings all this stuff together.
وهي حدث يجمع كل تلك الأمور معاً.
So in many ways, I am parents' dream
لذا، أنا أمثل من عدة نواحٍ، ما يحلم به الأهل
of how somebody can turn a sedentary lifestyle of playing video games
بأن يحول أحد ما نمط حياة ألعاب الفيديو قليل الحركة
into an actual career that pays real money.
إلى مهنة حقيقية تدر مالاً حقيقياً.
So when I get invited to an event like this,
لذا، عندما أدعى إلى حدث كهذا،
I'm sure that all of you expect me to get up here and say,
أنا على يقين أنكم جميعاً تنتظرون مني أن أقف هنا وأقول
"Games are awesome for your children."
"الألعاب رائعة من أجل أطفالكم"
Right? Because I'm a games guy and this is how I make my living.
صحيح؟ لأنني رجل ألعاب وهكذا أجني معيشتي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Games will help children.
الألعاب سوف تساعد الأطفال
But instead, I want to ask you a different question,
ولكن بدلاً من ذلك، أود ان أسألكم سؤالاً مختلفاً،
which is: Really, who needs games help?
وهو: من يحتاج لمساعدة الألعاب؟
I started this process by thinking about reading a particular article
لقد بدأتُ هذه العملية بالتفكير في قراءة مقالة معينة
in the New York Times recently.
في مجلة نيويورك تايمز مؤخراً.
In the article, a neuroscientist was talking about
في تلك المقالة، تتحدث عالمة أعصاب عن
how children were presenting themselves with attention deficit disorder.
كيف يقدم الأطفال أنفسهم مع اضطراب نقص الانتباه.
Their parents would come in and say,
سيأتي آباؤهم ويقولون،
"My kids can't possibly have ADD,
"لا يمكن أن يعاني أطفالي من هذا الاضطراب،
because they're super good at focusing on video games,
لأن قدرتهم خارقة بالتركيز على ألعاب الفيديو،
But when they go to school, they're really bad."
لكنهم في المدرسة سيئون جداً."
The neuroscientist was debunking this idea in the article.
كانت عالمة الأعصاب تنفي هذه الفكرة في المقالة.
She trotted out researchers like Dr Christopher Lucas at NYU,
كانت تستشهد بكلام باحثين مثل د.كريستوفر لوكاس في جامعة نيويورك،
who said games don't teach the right kind of attention skills
والذي قال أن الألعاب لا تعلم الأطفال النوع الصحيح من التركيز
where kids have sustained attention,
حيث يحافظ الأطفال على تركيزهم،
where they're not receiving regular rewards.
في الوقت الذي لا يتلقون تقديراً متكرراً.
And she trotted out experts
كما استعرضت خبراء
like Dr Dimitri Christakis at the University of Washington,
مثل د. ديمتري كريستاكيس من جامعة واشنطن،
who said that kids who play a lot of video games
ويقول أن الأطفال الذين يلعبون ألعاب الفيديو بكثرة
may find the real world unpalatable or uninteresting,
قد يجدون العالم الحقيقي غير مستساغ وغير ممتع،
as a result of their sensitization to games.
كنتيجة إحساسهم بالألعاب.
So I sat there and thought to myself, I'm scratching my head,
فجلست أفكر وأنا أحك رأسي
is it that our children have ADD,
هل يعاني أطفالنا من اضراب نقص الانتباه،
or is our world just too freaking slow for our children to appreciate?
أم أن عالمنا بطيء جداً بالنسبة لأطفالنا فلا يقدّروه؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Seriously, consider the picture you're looking at right now,
حقاً، فكروا بالصورة التي أمامكم،
like in my era, even my grandfather's era,
في عصري، بل وفي عصر جدي،
sitting down on a Sunday afternoon to read a good book with a cup of tea --
كنا نسترخي بعد ظهر يوم الأحد لقراءة كتاب ممتع مع فنجان شاي ...
I just have to say,
ولكن يجب أن أقول،
I don't think that today's kids are ever going to do that.
لا أعتقد أن أطفال اليوم سيقومون بشيء كهذا
The evidence is found in the games they play.
ونجد الدليل في الألعاب التي يلعبونها.
Consider the video game "World of Warcraft."
لنفكر بلعبة "وورلد أوف ووركرافت"
When I was growing up,
عندما تربيت،
the maximum skill that I was expected to display in a video game
كانت أقصى مهارة مطلوبة مني في لعبة فيديو
was simple hand-eye coordination,
هي تنسيق بسيط بين اليد والعين،
a joystick and a firing button.
قبضة التحكم وزر إطلاق النار.
Today's kids play games in which they're expected to chat
اليوم، يلعب الأطفال بألعاب تتطلب منهم التحدث
in text and voice,
بالكتابة والصوت،
operate a character, follow long- and short-term objectives,
وتشغيل الشخصية، ومتابعة الأهداف الطويلة والقصيرة المدى
and deal with their parents interrupting them all the time to talk to them.
والتعامل مع مقاطعة أهلهم كل الوقت للتحدث.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Kids have to have an extraordinary multitasking skill
يجب أن يمتلك الأطفال مهارة تعدد مهام غير عادية
to be able to achieve things today.
حتى يستطيعوا تحقيق أشياء اليوم.
We never had to have that.
لم يكن ذلك مطلوب منا.
It turns out things like that actually make you smarter.
وكما يبدو، فأشياء كهذه تجعل المرء أذكى بالفعل.
Research by Arne May et Al at the University of Regensburg in Germany
قام بحث لآرن ماي وآخرون في جامعة ريغنسبورغ في ألمانيا
found that when they gave participants -- this was actually done on adults --
بإعطاء المشاركين --وقد كانوا من البالغين--
a simple task to learn, like juggling,
مهمة بسيطة ليتعلموها، كاللعب بالكرات
in 12 weeks,
خلال 12 أسبوع،
people who were asked to learn juggling
أولئك الذين طلب منهم تعلم اللعب بالكرات
displayed a marked increase in gray matter in their brain.
قد أظهروا ازدياداً كبيراً في المادة الرمادية في الدماغ
On an MRI, you can see people get more gray matter
يظهر تصوير الرنين المغناطيسي ازدياد المادة الرمادية لدى الأشخاص
after 12 weeks of learning juggling.
بعد 12 أسبوع من تعلم اللعب بالكرات.
In 2008, they went back and redid the study
في عام 2008، قاموا بإعادة الدراسة
to see why the gray matter increased.
ليكتشفوا سبب ازدياد المادة الرمادية.
They discovered it was the act of learning
وتبين أن عملية التعلم
that produced the increased brain matter,
هي التي أنتجت ازدياد المادة الرمادية
not performance at the activity itself,
وليس تنفيذ النشاط بحد ذاته،
which is a very interesting finding.
وهذه نتيجة مثيرة للانتباه جداً.
It also reinforced this idea, which should go over well here as well,
وقد عززت هذه الفكرة التي ستفيدنا هنا
that multilingual people outperform monolingual people
بأن أداء الناس الناطقين بأكثر من لغة يضاهي أداء أحاديي اللغة
on most standardized tests by about 15%.
في معظم الاختبارات القياسية بنسبة 15%.
There's something that happens in the brain from that kind of activity.
هناك شيء يحدث في الدماغ بسبب هذا النوع من النشاط.
Andrea Kuszewski, speaking at Harvard, talked about
تحدثت أندريا كوسزيفيسكي في هافارد،
these five things that people do to increase their grey matter
عن الأشياء الـ5 التي يقوم بها الناس لزيادة المادة الرمادية لديهم
and to teach themselves to increase their fluid intelligence.
وليعلموا أنفسهم كيف يرفعون من ذكائهم السلس.
"Fluid intelligence" is the intelligence we use to problem-solve.
"الذكاء السلس" هو الذكاء الذي نستخدمه في حل المشاكل.
It's different from crystalline intelligence,
وهو مختلف عن الذكاء المتبلور،
it helps us problem-solve.
فهو يساعدنا في حل المشاكل.
She identified, from the research,
من خلال البحوثات، قامت بتحديد
that there were five things you could do:
خمسة أشياء يمكن القيام بها:
seek novelty,
السعي للتجديد،
challenge yourself,
تحدي الذات،
think creatively,
التفكير بطريقة إبداعية،
do things the hard way
إنجاز أمور بطريقة صعبة،
and network.
والتواصل الاجتماعي.
Think about those five things.
فكروا بهذه الأمور الخمسة.
Any of you play video games?
هل تلعبون ألعاب الفيديو؟
Does it resemble the basic pattern of a video game to you in any way?
هل تشبه هذه الأمور النمط الأساسي لألعاب الفيديو بطريقة ما؟
These are five things that recur in all very successful video games.
هذه خمسة أشياء تتكرر في كل لعبة فيديو فائقة النجاح.
It also is connected to a constant and exponential increase in learning.
كما يرتبط هذا بتزايد ثابت ومتسارع في التعلم.
Video games fundamentally present a continuous process of learning to users.
بشكل أساسي، تقدم ألعاب الفيديو لمستخدميها عملية تعلم متواصلة.
They don't just learn for a little while and then stop.
فهم لا يتعلمون لفترة قصيرة ثم يتوقفون.
They're constantly evolving and moving forward.
بل يتطورون ويتقدمون بشكل مستمر.
It may, in fact, help us to explain the Flynn effect, finally.
كما يمكن لها أن تشرح "تأثير فلن" أخيراً.
The "Flynn effect," for those of you who don't know,
ولمن لا يعرفه، "تأثير فلن"
is the pattern that human intelligence is actually rising over time.
هو نمط ازدياد الذكاء البشري مع الوقت.
So if we look at the history of IQ, people, in fact, are getting smarter.
فإذا نظرنا إلى تاريخ نسب الذكاء، نرى أن الناس يصبحون أكثر ذكاءً.
In the US right now,
الآن في الولايات المتحدة،
average IQ is rising at .36 points of IQ per year.
يرتفع متوسط نسب الذكاء بمعدل 0.36 نقطة في العام.
What's been very interesting is that in some countries --
وماهو مثير للاهتمام أنه في بعض الدول
not to call anyone out, but Denmark and Norway --
- وبدون ذكر أسماء، لكن الدنمارك والنرويج-
in some countries, overall crystalline IQ
في بعض الدول، نسب الذكاء المتبلور الكلية
has stopped or slowed down or declined.
توقفت أو تباطأت أو انخفضت.
In other countries, though,
ولكن في دول أخرى،
particularly when looking at fluid IQ, fluid intelligence,
وتحديداً عند النظر إلى نسب الذكاء السلس،
the number is increasing,
نرى أن الرقم يرتفع،
and the rate of fluid intelligence increase is increasing,
كما أن معدل ارتفاعه هو أيضاً في تزايد
starting in the 1990s.
ابتداءً من التسعينيات.
Coincidence? I think not.
هل هذا صدفة؟ لا أعتقد ذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In fact, games are wired to produce a particular kind of reaction in people.
في الواقع، إن الألعاب مصممة لتولد ردة فعل محددة لدى الناس.
So we've got this learning brain increase,
لدينا الازدياد في قدرة الدماغ على التعلم
multitasking brain increase connection,
وازدياد الترابط في تعدد المهام في الدماغ
and we also have a strong dopamine loop in the brain.
كما يوجد حلقة قوية من الناقل العصبي في الدماغ.
As games present a challenge,
بما أن الألعاب تشكّل تحدياً
and you struggle to achieve that challenge and you overcome it,
وتسعى جاهداً لمواجهته والتغلب عليه
dopamine is released in your brain.
يتم اطلاق الناقل العصبي في دماغك
And that produces an intrinsic reinforcement.
وهذا ينتج تعزيزاً أساسياً
In the words of Judy, that produces an intrinsic reinforcement
كما تقول جودي، ينتج هذا تعزيزاً أساسياً
that causes you to go back
يقودك للعودة
and keep seeking that activity over and over again.
والسعي وراء هذا النشاط مراراً وتكراراً
So this is really powerful stuff.
هذه أشياء قوية جداً.
I want to introduce you to an educator who understands this in intricate detail,
أود أن أعرفكم على معلم يفهم هذه التفاصيل المعقدة
named Ananth Pai.
ويدعى أنانيث باي.
Ananth was a very successful businessperson
كان أنانيث رجل أعمال فائق النجاح
who worked on process reengineering.
عمل على إعادة هيكلة إدارة الأعمال.
When his kids went into school in White Bear Lake, Minnesota,
عندما ذهب أولاده الى المدرسة في وايت بير ليك، مينيسوتا
a suburb of Minneapolis-Saint Paul,
وهي من ضواحي منيابولس سانت بول،
he saw the education system
اطلع على النظام التعليمي
and decided he wanted to do something about it.
وقرر أن يقوم بعمل شيء حياله.
So as an adult, he went back and got a master's in [Education]
بما أنه شخص بالغ، درس وحصل على شهادة ماجستير في التربية
and took over a class at White Bear Lake Elementary School.
واستلم صفاً في مدرسة وايت بير ليك.
Ananth Pai replaced the standard curriculum
استبدل أنانيث باي المنهاج المعتمد
with a video game based curriculum of his own design,
بمنهاج يعتمد على ألعاب الفيديو من تصميمه،
separating the kids into leaning styles
وفصل الأطفال إلى أنماط تعليم مختلفة
and giving them Nintendo DS's and computer games --
وأعطاهم ألعاب نينتندو دي أس وألعاب كمبيوتر
everything off the shelf, nothing custom --
كل شيء مما كان متوفراً لا شيء خاص
giving them Nintendo DS's and computer games
أعطاهم هذه الألعاب
that were both individual and social to play,
التي كانت فردية وجماعية
that taught them math and language.
وعلمتهم الرياضيات واللغة.
Let me tell you what happened.
دعوني أخبركم ما الذي حدث.
In the space of 18 weeks,
خلال 18 أسبوع،
Mr. Pai's class went from a below-3rd-grade level
انتقل صف السيد باي من مستوى أدنى من الصف الثالث
in reading and math
في القراءة والرياضيات
to a mid-4th-grade level in reading and math.
إلى منتصف الصف الرابع في القراءة والرياضيات.
In 18 weeks of a game-based curriculum.
خلال 18 أسبوع من منهاج قائم على الألعاب.
More importantly, when you talk to the children,
والأهم من ذلك، عندما تتحدث إلى الأطفال
when they're interviewed on television, even away from Mr. Pai,
وعند القيام بمقابلات تلفزيونية معهم حتى لو كانت بعيداً عن السيد باي
they say two things over and over again,
يرددون مراراً وتكراراً أن أمرين
that help them learn in his class:
ساعدوهما بالتعلم في الصف
learning is fun,
التعلم أمر ممتع،
and learning is multiplayer.
والتعلم أمر جماعي.
Whether they use those exact words or not,
بغض النظر عن دقة الكلمات التي يستخدمونها
they say learning is fun and learning is multiplayer.
مجمل كلامهم هو أن التعلم ممتع وجماعي.
This is the key to making that experience really successful for kids.
هذا كان الأمر الأساسي الذي جعل التجربة ناجحة للأطفال.
It's also true, though, that we need to talk about
ولكن لابد لنا أن نتحدث عن
the relationship between kids and violence in games.
العلاقة بين الأطفال والعنف في الألعاب.
Study after study very clearly tells you
تتحدث الدراسات المتتالية بشكل واضح أن
that violent games do not make children violent.
الألعاب العنيفة لا تجعل الأطفال عنيفين.
We also must acknowledge, however,
ولكن يجب أن نعترف
that if you have a child predisposed to violence,
أنه إذا كان لديك طفل مستعد للعنف
violent games may help make them a better violent child.
ستساعد الألعاب العنيفة على جعله طفلاً عنيفاُ.
If they train kids to do other things, they also will train that,
إذا كانت تدرب الأطفال على أشياء أخرى، فسيتدربون على ذلك.
and we need to accept that,
يجب أن نقبل هذا،
and we need to start understanding the connection
ويجب أن نبدأ بفهم العلاقة
between games as a form of training.
بين الألعاب كطريقة للتدريب.
We can't blanket-say that they don't affect kids.
لا يمكننا أن نقول أن الألعاب لا تؤثر على الأطفال
It's not true.
هذا ليس صحيحاً.
I'd like to call the group of people who are driving this trend forward
أود أن أسمي جماعة الناس الذين يقودون هذا التوجه
"Generation G."
"جيل G"
There are 126 million millennials in the United States and the EU,
يوجد 126 مليون شخص من جيل الألفية في الولايات المتحدة وأوروبا
plus younger kids we can't yet count,
بالإضافة للأطفال الأصغر سناً ولا يمكن عدهم
that form Generation G.
الذين يكونون جيل G
And the way that Generation G is different from X, Y,
والطريقة التي يختلف فيها جيل G من "X" أو "Y"،
and all the different generations that we may belong to,
أو كل الأجيال المختلفة التي قد ننتمي لها
is that video games are the primary form of entertainment
هي أن ألعاب الفيديو هي طريقة التسلية الأساسية
that Generation G is consuming.
التي يستهلكها جيل G
It is their primary form of entertainment.
إنها وسيلة تسليتهم الأولى
This is already starting to have a tremendous effect on society.
وبدأ تأثير هذا يظهر بشكل كبير على المجتمع.
All around us, Generation G's desire for game-like experiences
أينما نظرنا، تقوم رغبة أفراد جيل G بعيش تجارب شبيهة بالألعاب
is reshaping industries,
بإعادة صياغة الصناعات
from Foursquare, which caused the mobile social networking ecosystem to start,
من شركة فورسكوير التي بدأت نظام شبكات الموبايل الاجتماعية البيئي
to companies like Nike, Coke, Chase, and also Kozinga,
إلى شركات مثل نايكي، كوكا كولا، تشيس و كوزينغا
which owes much of its success to games.
التي يعود معظم نجاحها للألعاب.
The trend that underlies this whole pattern is called "gamification."
والتوجه الذي يمثل أساس هذا النمط يدعى "التلعيب"
It's a word that many of you, I'm sure, have heard.
وأنا متأكد أم معظمكم قد سمع بهذه الكلمة.
A simple definition of gamification is it's the process of using game thinking
وبشكل بسيط، يعرف التلعيب على أنه عملية استخدام تفكير الألعاب
and game mechanics
وآليات الألعاب
to engage audiences and solve problems.
لإشغال الجمهور وحل المشاكل.
Part of the reason gamification has become such an emergent topic right now
وجزء من السبب الذي جعل التلعيب موضوعاً طارئاً في الوقت الحالي
is because of Generation G's effect on culture and society already.
هو أثر جيل G على الثقافة والمجتمع.
Their expectations are different.
لديهم تطلعات مختلفة.
Some examples of gamification that you may have seen
بعض أمثلة التلعيب التي قد صادفتموها
that are really fascinating to me
والتي أجدها مدهشة جداَ
are the emergence of in-dash[board] games in cars.
هو ظهور الألعاب المدمجة في لوحة قيادة السيارة.
Today, if you buy a hybrid or an electric vehicle,
اليوم، إذا اشتريت سيارة هجينة أو كهربائية
you'll almost certainly see
على الأغلب سترى
the product of a hundred million dollars' worth of tooling
منتجات بقيمة مئة مليون دولار من آلات
and research and development,
وأبحاث وتطوير
in the form of a Tamagotchi-style game,
على نمط ألعاب تماغوتشي
in a dashboard designed to make you a more ecological driver.
في لوحة قيادة مصممة لتجعلك سائقاً بيئياً بشكل أكبر
Most of the game mechanics are very simple:
معظم آليات الألعاب بسيطة جداً:
a plant grows as you drive more ecologically
في كل مرة تقود بشكل بيئي تنمو نبتة
and withers if you don't,
وتذبل نبتة في حال لم تقم بذلك.
like those virtual pets Tamagotchi.
كما حال حيوانات تماغوتشي الافتراضية
This is an example of gamification at work.
هذا مثال عن التلعيب المطبق.
Another really interesting example is a thing called "speed camera lottery,"
أحد الأمثلة الأخرى المثيرة هو ما يدعى "يانصيب كاميرا السرعة"
designed by Kevin Richardson, based in San Francisco, works for MTV.
الذي صممه كيفن ريتشاردسون في سان فرنسيسكو والذي يعمل لدى MTV
Awesome guy.
إنه شاب رائع
This is the concept in speed camera lottery:
وهذا هو مبدأ "يانصيب كاميرا السرعة"
you know those speeding cameras that you pass by,
أتعرفون كاميرات السرعة التي تتجاوزونها
and they take your picture and send you a ticket?
والتي تلتقط صوركم ثم يرسلون لكم مخالفة؟
In many Scandinavian countries,
في معظم الدول الإسكندنافية
the ticket you get is actually based not only on how fast you were going,
لا تعتمد مخالفتك على مدى سرعتك فحسب
but how much money you make: the more you make, the bigger the ticket.
بل على مقدار دخلك. كلما كان دخلك أعلى، كانت مخالفتك أكبر.
Kevin reengineered a speeding camera in Sweden
أعاد كيفن تصميم كاميرا سرعة في السويد
that instead of just giving tickets
فبدلاً من مجرد إعطاء مخالفة
to people who drive over the speed limit that pass the camera,
للأشخاص الذين يتجاوزون حدود السرعة عند تجاوز الكاميرا،
anybody who drives under the limit is entered into a lottery
يدخل أي شخص يقود أقل من الحد في سحب يانصيب
to win the proceeds of the people who speed.
ليربحوا من عائدات المسرعين
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It is game thinking -- that term I described earlier,
هذا تفكير بطريقة ألعاب-- المصطلح الذي استخدمته سابقاً
the core foundation of gamification --
الجوهر الأساسي للتلعب
in its purest and most beautiful form:
في صيغته الأكثر صفاء وجمالاً:
take a big, negative reinforcement loop
خذ حلقة تعزيز كبيرة سلبية
and turn it into small, incremental positive reinforcement loop.
وحوّلها إلى حلقة تعزيز إضافية إيجابية
It had the effect of dropping speed by over 20% at that point of intervention.
هذا له تأثير خفض السرعة بما يتجاوز 20% في لحظة التدخل.
Corporations have also become aware of the trend of gamification
وقد أصبحت الشركات مدركةً لتوجه التلعيب
and the effect of games on people like Generation G.
وأثر الألعاب على الناس مثل جيل G.
Gartner Group says that by 2015,
تقول مجموعة غارتنر أنه بحلول 2015،
70% of all the Global 2000, the biggest companies in the world,
70% من غلوبال 2000، أكبر الشركات في العالم
will be actively using gamification,
ستستخدم التلعيب بشكل فعال،
and 50% of their process of innovation
و50% من عمليات الابتكار لديهم
will be gamified,
ستصبح ملعبة
which is an astonishing thing.
وهذا شيء مدهش.
It's a huge change.
وهذا تغيير كبير.
What this all points to is a future that looks pretty different
كل هذا يشير إلى مستقبل مختلف جداً
from the world we live in today.
من العالم الذي نعيش فيه اليوم.
Generation G and those driving the gamification meme forward,
يقوم جيل G وأولئك الذين يقودون سلوك التلعيب للأمام
are advocating for a different world.
بتأييد عالم مختلف.
It's a world in which things move at faster pace
وهو عالم تتحرك فيه الأشياء بوتيرة أسرع
than they did for you and me.
مما نعرفها.
It's a world in which there are rewards everywhere
وهو عالم يحوي مكافآت في كل مكان
for actions that people take.
للأعمال التي يقوم بها الناس.
The rewards don't always have to be cash rewards.
وهي ليست بالضرورة مكافآت نقدية،
They can be meaningful status rewards,
بل يمكن أن تكون جوائز مكانة معنوية،
meaningful access rewards,
أو جوائز انضمام،
meaningful power rewards.
أو جوائز قوة،
A world in which there's extensive collaborative play.
يوجد في ذلك العالم لعب تعاوني شامل.
This is one of the things that Generation G does so much differently
وهذه أحد الأشياء التي يقوم بها جيل G بشكل مختلف جداً
than even my generation.
حتى عن جيلي.
I remember going to school and teachers struggling to come up with exercises
أتذكر عندما كنت في المدرسة، كان المعلمون يجدون صعوبة بتحضير تمارين
that we could do as a team,
يمكننا القيام بها كفريق
that would be graded as a team.
ويمكن تقييمها كفريق.
In the end, those group exercises always boiled down to an individual score,
في النهاية، كانت التمارين الجماعية تنتهي دائماً برصيد فردي
which distorted the way that people behaved.
مما يحرّف طريقة تصرّف الناس.
But, Generation G plays a lot of games
ولكن جيل G يلعب الكثير من الألعاب
that are purely collaborative, in which there is group value.
وهي تعاونية بحتة تحتوي على قيم الجماعة.
This will also affect our world in untold ways.
وهذا سيؤثر على عالمنا بطرق غير معدودة
And, Generation G, the fun future, is a much more global world.
وجيل G، المستقبل المرح، هو عالم متعولم بشكل أكبر.
It turns out that we are already out of touch.
كما يبدو، نحن الآن بعيدون.
We are the generation most out of touch with our future or current children
نحن جيل بعيد عن أطفالنا المستقبليين والحاليين
than any generation in history.
أكثر من أي جيل في التاريخ.
We like to think that baby boomers' parents were the most out-of-touch people
نحب أن نفكر أن أهل طفرة المواليد هم الأكثر ابتعاداً
in the world.
في العالم.
They're the ones who had to deal with the summer of love
كان عليهم أن يتعاملوا مع صيف الحب
and sex and drugs and all that kind of stuff.
والجنس والمخدرات وكل هذه الأمور.
We still make phone calls.
لازلنا نجري مكلمات هاتفية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I mean, we are the ones with the problem,
أعني أنه نحن من يعاني من المشاكل
and we are going to be the most out-of-touch generation in history.
ونحن سنصبح أكثر جيل بعيد في التاريخ
Of course, it's also true, and I'm here to tell you:
طبعاً هذا صحيح، أنا هنا لأخبركم
the kids are alright.
أن الأطفال على ما يرام
They're going to be just fine.
سيكونون بخير.
We don't need to worry, strictly speaking,
حرفياً، لا داعي للقلق
about kids and games, and the effect that it will have on the world.
على الأطفال والألعاب، وأثرها على العالم.
Not just are the kids are going to be alright;
ولن يكون الأطفال على ما يرام فحسب،
frankly, the kids are going to be awesome.
بصراحة، سيكونون رائعين.
But it's going to take your help to make the kids awesome.
لكن سيتطلب الأمر مساعتكم لجعل الأطفال رائعين.
I have a prescription for you.
لدي وصفة لكم.
This is the best prescription anybody is ever going to write in your life.
وهذه أفضل وصفة ستكتب لكم طوال حياتكم.
I'm going to write it for you right now,
وسأكتبها لكم الآن
in your mind, I don't have an actual pad.
في عقلكم، فليس لدي قلم حقيقي.
Just for clarity, a disclaimer: I'm not a doctor.
وللتوضيح وإخلاء المسؤولية، أنا لست طبيباً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I am, however, going to write a prescription for you all.
ولكني سأكتب لكم وصفة.
This is the prescription:
وهذه هي:
if you have children or you work with children,
إذا كان لديكم أطفال أو كنتم تعملون مع الأطفال،
or you desire to work with children, or you want to change he world,
أو إذا كنتم ترغبون بالعمل مع الأطفال، أو تودون تغيير العالم،
this is the absolute, positive best thing that you can do with your time,
إن أفضل شيء إيجابي يمكن أن تفعلوه في وقتكم
from now until I see you in the retirement home on the coast of Spain
من الآن حتى أراكم في منزل التقاعد على شواطئ إسبانيا
or in the virtual world,
أو في العالم الافتراضي
wherever you choose to retire,
في أي وقت تختاروه للتقاعد
which is: get into the game with your kids.
هذا الشيء هو: العبوا مع أطفالكم،
Stop fighting the game trend, if that's where you are right now.
كفوا عن محاربة توجه الألعاب، إذا كان هذا ما تفعلوه الآن.
Don't fight the game trend. Become one with the game.
لا تحاربوا توجه الألعاب. بل اتحدوا مع اللعبة.
Enter the game. Understand it.
ادخلوا في اللعبة، وافهموها.
Understand the dynamic of how your children play
افهموا الديناميكية التي يلعب بها أطفالكم
the games that they play.
والألعاب التي يلعبوها
Understand how their minds work from the context of the game outward,
افهموا كيف تعمل عقولهم بدءً من سياق اللعبة نحو الخارج
rather than from the world outside inward.
بدلاً من البدء بالعالم الخارجي نحو الداخل.
The world that we live in right now,
العالم الذي نعيش فيه الآن،
the world of Sunday afternoons, drinking a cup of herbal tea,
عالم شرب شاي الأعشاب بعد ظهر الأحد،
reading some old book, chilling out by the window,
وقراءة كتاب قديم والاسترخاء خارجاً بجانب الشرفة
is over.
قد انتهى.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that's okay.
وهذا أمر عادي.
There's a lot more things that we can do that are fun and engaging.
هناك أشياء أكثر يمكننا القيام بها ذات متعة وتعلق أكبر
If you take away one thing from today's presentation,
إذا تعلمتم شيئاً واحداً من عرض اليوم
I hope it is you get a chance to go play with your kids.
أتمنى أن يكون إمكانية اللعب مع أطفالكم.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)